Guide to the United Ministries in Higher Education Records - Addendum A
Yale University Divinity School Library
United Ministries in Higher Education Records - Addendum A
1960-1991
RG 104A
Yale University Divinity School Library
6
(13 boxes)
Organizational and program materials of UMHE and related bodies provide insight on Protestant campus ministries. United Ministries in Higher Education was established in 1964, emerging out of the United Campus Christian Fellowship, a body that represented the student Christian movements of four Protestant denominations. By 1968 six more denominational agencies had joined the UMHE to promote ecumenical cooperation in religious work among college and university students. In 1979 UMHE changed its name to United Ministries in Education, joining with Ministries in Public Education. In 1988 this partnership was ended and the UMHE was reorganized as The Higher Education Ministries Team of United Ministries in Higher Education.
United Ministries in Higher Education
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of UMHE.
Biographical / Historical
United Ministries in Higher Education evolved out of several decades of ministry in non-church related institutions of higher education in the U.S. Organizationally, UMHE emerged out of the United Campus Christian Fellowship, which was a uniting in 1960 of the student Christian movements of the Evangelical United Brethren Church, the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), the United Church of Christ, and the United Presbyterian Church. These UCCF denominations formed UMHE in 1964 and by 1968 six more denominations had joined forces: the Moravian Church (1965), the Presbyterian Church, U.S. (1966), the Church of the Brethren (1967), the Episcopal Church (1968), the Reformed Church in America (1968), and the American Baptist Church (1968). The United Methodist Church became a member at its formation - the uniting of the Methodist Church with the Evangelical United Brethren church. In 1976, the Reformed Church in America restructured and withdrew from participation.
In 1966 the United Campus Christian Fellowship merged into the University Christian Movement in the United States, a body that was not integrally related to the institutional church in the same way that the UCCF had been. The UMHE continued to pursue its goal of developing strategy and recommending policy for ministries in higher education for the denominations it represented that would lead to common initiatives rather than unilateral actions.
From 1964 to 1968 UMHE was governed by a Council for Policy and Strategy, a Committee of Administrators, and a Secretariat. In the fall of 1968, the National Commission for United Ministries in Higher Education was formed by the ten national denominational agencies that were supporting UMHE, a restructuring intended to place discussion and decision making in the hands of a more representative body of persons, to clarify staff accountability, and to improve the coordination of the campus ministries of the denominations. A Self-Study Committee was established in 1973 to oversee an extensive organizational analysis that led to the formation of a UMHE Policy Board in 1974.
The Policy Board of UMHE and the Program and Policy Committee of an organization called Ministries in Public Education created a Joint UMHE-MPE Committee in 1978 to investigate means for closer working and organizational relations between the two ministries. This Committee recommended the formation of United Ministries in Education as the successor to MPE and UHME. This change in the name and purpose of UMHE was consented to by the New York State Education Department on August 24, 1979.
The partnership between UMHE and MPE was dissolved in 1988 and The Higher Education Ministries Team of United Ministries in Higher Education was officially constituted on November 15, 1989 for a three-year period beginning January 1, 1990 (still operating under the corporate name of United Ministries in Education). UMHE was empowered to pursue an agenda in higher education ministries during this period of evaluation of both the program and the organization itself. Denominations supporting the Team included the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), the Episcopal Church, the United Church of Christ, the Presbyterian Church U.S.A., the Moravian Church, and the Church of the Brethren. The role of UMHE in relation to denominational activities and the new Higher Education Ministries Arena of the National Council of Churches was evaluated.
Scope and Contents
These records continue the documentation provided by Record Group No. 104 and complement other holdings at the Yale Divinity Library, including Record Group No. 54: Archives of the New England Commission for United Ministries in Higher Education (1967-1974), Record Group No. 64: Archives of the National Campus Ministry Association, and Record Group No. 62, Records of the Danforth Study of Campus Ministries, as well as the archives of various student Christian movements. The constellation of these various record groups provides opportunity for study of the complex mix of ecumenical and denominational efforts at religious work on campuses in the U.S.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence and Office Files, 1975-1989
II. Organization and Policy Records, 1960-1989
III. Program Files and Reports, 1963-1989
IV. Publications, 1960-1991
V. Financial Records, 1969-1989
VI. Related Material, 1982-1985
Church work with students -- United States; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Clergy; United Ministries in Higher Education
- Correspondence and Office Files, 1975-1989; Series I
  - Correspondence and Mailings, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Homeland Ministries, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Presbyterians and Moravians, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memos of Higher Education Ministry Team, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from the Communications Office-Betsy Alden, 1987 Jun - 1988 Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from the Communications Office-Betsy Alden, 1986 May - 1987 Jul (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with the Church of the Brethren, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Organization and Policy Records, 1960-1989; Series II
  - Minutes of Executive and Staff Meetings, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reports and Proposals, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Minutes of Community College Committee, 1973-81 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Notes of Community College Committee, 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Incorporation Papers, Status Report, and By Laws, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Certificate of incorporation, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Policy Board Meeting, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  - Staff Meeting, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Basic Policy Statements, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Staff Meeting, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Proposal for a National Network, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Annual Meeting Reports and Proposals, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Minutes of Higher Education Ministry Team (HEMT), 1989 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - HEMT Consultation, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Directory, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - UCCF National Council, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - National Student Christian Federation, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Annual Meeting, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Minutes of Staff Meeting, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Minutes of Staff Meeting, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Annual Meeting, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Planning Committee, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Minutes of Executive Meeting, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Executive Director's Responsibility (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Administration Coordinator's Portfolio (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Minutes of Ministry Team meeting, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Notes of Staff Meeting, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Basic Policies (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Minutes of Staff Meeting, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Staff Meeting, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Staff Meeting, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Minutes of Administration meeting, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Minutes of Executive Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 46-47)
  - Minutes of National Commission on Higher Education, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Minutes of Staff Meeting, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Minutes of Community College Meeting, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Junior College Dialogue Group, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Policy Board Meeting, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Western Region Staff Committee, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Policy Board Workbook, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Staff Meeting, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Policy Board Meeting, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Goals and Objectives, 1974-79 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Report of Examination, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Community College Report, 1974-75 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Policy Board Meetings, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 60-61)
  - Executive Committee meetings, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 62-63)
  - National Staff Meeting minutes, 1967-1970 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Community College Committee, 1973-1978 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Community College Reports, 1974-1978 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Community College Evaluation Report, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Denominational Executives, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Policy Team Meeting, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Minutes of Annual Meeting, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Minutes of Staff Meeting, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Dissertation abstract: An Historical Appraisal by Yeaney (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Minutes of the Policy Board, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Denominational Executives Meeting, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Minutes of Staff Meeting, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Policy Board Meeting on Restructure, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Minutes of Staff Meeting, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Minutes Of Denominational Executives Meeting, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - List of UMHE Materials at Presbyterian Historical Society (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - By Laws and Incorporation Status for NY and NC (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Denominational Executives Meeting, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Ecumenical Relations Meeting, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Policies, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Report on Restructuring, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Policy Board Roster, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Minutes of Policy Board Meeting, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Minutes of Policy Board Meeting, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 87)
- Program Files and Program Reports, 1963-1989; Series III
  - Planning Study "Delphi Process", 1972 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Planning Study "Cross Purpose Matrix", 1972 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Community College Program, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Cleveland Week, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Message to Vietnam, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Proposal for United Ministries in Education, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Afro-Asian Study Seminar, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Latin American Study Seminar, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - The Covenant, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - The Congregation and Ministry in Higher Education, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - Review of Partnership for Missions Team, 1982-1986 (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Science and Technology Consultation, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 99)
  - Peacemaking, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Aesthetics, Theology and Education, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - Community College Report, 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - Survey on the Church and Education, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - Local Church and Community College (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - Ten Programs, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - Plan of ministry, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Programs in Health and Human Services, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Program Report, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - Program Reports, 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 110)
- Publications, 1960-1991; Series IV
  - Publications about government funding of college education, 1960's (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Student Christian Movement publications, 1960's (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - "Search For Authentic Self" (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - September Undergraduate (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Serpent Coiled Within (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - The Source Vol 1, No 2, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - God's People in Mission (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Campus Publications, 1960's (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Report from the Campus (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - The Day the Country Mouse Expired (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Federation News, No.1, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Renewal And Radical Change, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Lutherian and Presbyterian publications, 1960's (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - Campus Publications, 1960's (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Ultimate questions in penultimate form (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - University, Church and Internationalization (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Violence: No Resort or Last Resort or.. .? (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Urbanization and the University (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Campus newspapers and publications, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - "Is Ed. a Human Issue?" and "A Neglected Ministry" (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - The Shifting Sands of Campus Ministry (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Connexion, 1973-1988 (Box 11, Folder 121-125)
  - Presbyterian Missions and Ministry Publications, 1980's (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - Profiles of Ministry in Higher Education, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 127)
- Financial Records, 1969-1989; Series V
  - Certification of Incorporation, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 128)
  - Financial Statement, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 129)
  - Reports on Not For Profit Status, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 130)
  - Tax Exempt Status, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Certification of Incorporation, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - Corporation Deposit and Tax Identification Number, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - Treasury Review, Contract, and Budget, 1987-1989 (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - Financial Plan and Budget, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - Tax Exempt Status, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 136)
  - Incorporation and Restructuring Papers, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - Financial Report, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - Financial Statement, 1975, 1978-1981 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - Financial Statement, 1982-1989 (Box 12, Folder 140)
- Related Material, 1982-1985; Series VI
  - Partnerships for Mission, 1984-1986 (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - Partnerships for Mission, 1982-1985 (Box 13, Folder 142-143)
  - The Church and Education, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - Missions Network, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 145)
  - UME Convocation, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 146)
  - UME Handbook and Bible Studies, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 147)